<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>News on M²LInES</title><link>/news/</link><description>Recent content in News on M²LInES</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title> 2021 CESM workshop</title><link>/news/cesmworkshop/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/cesmworkshop/</guid><description>M²LInES team members will present at Machine Learning session for the CESM workshop on June 17. Info and agenda here</description></item><item><title> Call for Papers for JAMES</title><link>/news/5jamescall/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/5jamescall/</guid><description>M²LInES members Janni Yuval, Pierre Gentine and Laure Zanna are part of the organizers of a special collection at JAMES (Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems) that will include both new ML methodologies developed for advancing Earth system science and ML applications to Earth system modeling. Papers submissions are open. The community is invited to contribute. More information here</description></item><item><title> M²LInES-related paper by PI Gentine</title><link>/news/4pierrepaper2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/4pierrepaper2/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Pierre Gentine is the senior author and Research Scientist Tom Beucler is the lead author in this new publication. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title> M²LInES-related paper by PI Le Sommer</title><link>/news/2julienpaper/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/2julienpaper/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Julien Le Sommer is a co-author in this new publication. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title> New paper by M²LInES members Guillaumin and Zanna</title><link>/news/1arthurpaper/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/1arthurpaper/</guid><description>In this paper, M²LInES postdoc Arthur Guillaumin and lead PI Laure Zanna developed a stochastic deep learning parametrization that is trained on high-resolution data from CM2.6, a coupled climate model. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title>M²LInES-related paper by PI Gentine</title><link>/news/3pierrepaper1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/news/3pierrepaper1/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Pierre Gentine is the senior author in this new publication. Research Scientist Tom Beucler is a co-author. Read their paper here</description></item></channel></rss>