<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>News on M²LInES</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/</link><description>Recent content in News on M²LInES</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 09:29:16 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://m2lines.github.io/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title> M²LInES at AGU 22</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2212agu22/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2212agu22/</guid><description>AGU M²LInES Highlights The M²LInES team is excited to present our recent scientific advances at the Fall 2022 AGU meeting in Chicago and online. Below is a summary of the talks (all times are CST). For your convenience, you can download the schedule for the talks by following this link.
Machine learning for physics discovery &amp;amp; modeling We have an extensive lineup of talks and posters from M²LInES team members and affiliates.</description></item><item><title> Direct observational evidence of an oceanic dual kinetic energy cascade and its seasonality</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211balwada/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211balwada/</guid><description>In this article, led by Dhruv Balwada, ocean drifter observations show wave and turbulence merge and split flows, simultaneously transferring energy to large and small scales.</description></item><item><title> Implicit learning of convective organization explains precipitation stochasticity</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211shamekh/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211shamekh/</guid><description>Cloud and convection take many structure and degrees of organization, which are still absent in most parameterizations. But does that structure matter for precipitation? This preprint, led by Sara Shamekh, proposes an elegant method to include organization in the parameterization of precipitation that results in a significant improvement in predicting precipitation, especially extremes, at GCM scale.</description></item><item><title> Ocean currents break up a tabular iceberg</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211adcroft/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211adcroft/</guid><description>This article examines the mechanism that led to the breakup of massive iceberg A68 in Dec 2020. The authors, including Alistair Adcroft, demonstrate that the A68a breakup event may have been triggered by ocean-current shear, a new breakup mechanism not previously reported. Their paper was featured in the news.</description></item><item><title> On Gradient Descent Convergence beyond the Edge of Stability</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211bruna/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211bruna/</guid><description>Joan Bruna is the senior author in this preprint on Gradient Descent (GD) convergence in unstable conditions. The study examines the conditions for such unstable convergence, focusing on simple, yet representative, learning problems.</description></item><item><title> A year-round satellite sea-ice thickness record from CryoSat-2</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2210bushuk/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2210bushuk/</guid><description>This study, co-authored by Mitch Bushuk, produced the first ever year-round satellite observational record of Arctic sea ice thickness, employing a deep learning model to produce estimates of sea ice freeboard. These data span the period 2010-2020 and will be critical for better monitoring the changing Arctic climate, advancing climate model evaluation, and improving sea ice predictions.</description></item><item><title> Comparing Storm Resolving Models and Climates via Unsupervised Machine Learning</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2210gentine/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2210gentine/</guid><description>High resolution data is overwhelming and this paper, co-authored by Pierre Gentine and Tom Beucler, tries to define an unsupervised machine learning technique to better compare Storm Resolving Climate Models (SRMs). Their analysis found that only six out of nine considered SRMs are dynamically consistent. This split among SRMs highlights the need to further investigate sub-grid parameterization choices.</description></item><item><title> Semi-automatic tuning of coupled climate models with multiple intrinsic timescales</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2210deshayes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2210deshayes/</guid><description>Using the two-scale Lorenz96 model, this article evaluates the potential of History Matching to tune a climate system with multi-scale dynamics. This semi-automatic tuning was more efficient when combined with physical expertise. Julie Deshayes and V Balaji are co-authors on this study.</description></item><item><title> Benchmarking of machine learning ocean subgrid parameterizations in an idealized model</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2208ross/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2208ross/</guid><description>In this work, led by Andrew Ross, with Ziwei Li, Pavel Perezhogin, Carlos Fernandez-Granda and Laure Zanna, we provide a framework for systematically benchmarking the offline and online performance of physical and ML-based subgrid parameterizations. We find that the choice of filtering operator is critical for performance. To help with interpretability, we also propose a novel equation-discovery approach combining linear regression and genetic programming which generalizes better than physical and neural network parameterizations.</description></item><item><title> Cloud-based framework for inter-comparing submesoscale permitting realistic ocean models</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2208uchida/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2208uchida/</guid><description>This study presents a cloud-based workflow for intercomparing high-resolution ocean models and provides an assessment of one of the most used parameterizations of ocean submesoscales. Julien Le Sommer, Ryan Abernathey, and Aurelie Albert contributed to the research.</description></item><item><title> Non-Linear Dimensionality Reduction with a VED to Understand Convective Processes in Climate Models</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2208behrens/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2208behrens/</guid><description>Pierre Gentine and Tom Beucler are co-authors in this article, which demonstrates that Variational Encoder Decoder structures (VED) are capable of learning and accurately reproducing convective processes in an aquaplanet superparameterized climate model simulation, while enabling interpretability and better understanding of sub-grid-scale physical processes.</description></item><item><title> A potential energy analysis of ocean surface mixed layers - Brandon Reichl</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2207reichl/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2207reichl/</guid><description>Analysis of the ocean mixed layer requires one to estimate its vertical extent, for which there are various definitions. In this paper, Brandon Reichl and co-authors, including Alistair Adcroft, show that using the potential energy anomaly to identify the mixed layer depth is practical and it offers conceptual benefits by directly linking to the physics of upper ocean vertical mixing.</description></item><item><title> New preprint led by Adam Subel on transfer learning</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2207subel/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2207subel/</guid><description>Adam Subel is the lead author in this article, which builds a framework to understand and implement transfer learning, a powerful machine learning technique for enabling generalization between datasets from different configurations of a system or of varying quality/quantity, in multiscale physical systems.</description></item><item><title> Subseasonal Earth System Prediction with CESM2 - Judith Berner</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2207berner/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2207berner/</guid><description>Judith Berner is a co-author in this article, which describes the design and prediction skill of two subseasonal prediction systems based on two configurations of the Community Earth System Model, version 2 (CESM2): with the Community Atmosphere Model and with Whole Atmosphere Community Climate Model as its atmospheric component. Both systems are compared to NOAA CFSv2 and ECMWF.</description></item><item><title> Deep Learning for Subgrid-Scale Turbulence Modeling in LES of the Convective Atmospheric Boundary Layer</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gentine-abernathey/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gentine-abernathey/</guid><description>This article, co-authored by Pierre Gentine and Ryan Abernathey, replaces the typically used physically based assumptions with deep learning in subgrid-scale modeling, in large eddy simulations of turbulence. They show that the latter performs better in a priori (offline) tests of atmospheric turbulence. The deep neural networks model also captures key statistics of turbulence in a posteriori (online) tests.</description></item><item><title> Lorenzo Zampieri - A machine learning correction model</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/zampieri2022/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/zampieri2022/</guid><description>Lorenzo Zampieri et al. illustrate in this preprint, a novel method based on ML for reducing the surface temperature errors of atmospheric reanalyses in sea-ice-covered regions of the Arctic. The corrected temperature can be employed to support polar research activities, and to better simulate the evolution of the interacting sea ice and ocean systems in numerical models.</description></item><item><title> Will Gregory - Network connectivity article</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gregory2022/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gregory2022/</guid><description>Will Gregory and co-authors hypothesized in this publication that regional biases in sea ice thickness may hinder the ability of CMIP6 models to reproduce an important atmospheric driver of summer sea ice variability, and hence their ability to make reliable sea ice predictions on seasonal to inter-annual time scales.</description></item><item><title> 2022 CESM workshop: Info and submission deadline</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/cesmworkshop2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/cesmworkshop2022/</guid><description>Registration is open for the 2022 CESM Workshop on June 13-16, 2022. Please visit the website to register as well as submit working group session talks and /or posters. The deadline to submit a talk / poster is Monday, May 16th.
The full workshop agenda can be found here.
In particular, Laure Zanna will give a joint plenary talk on M²LInES with Galen McKinley from LEAP.</description></item><item><title> Anastasiia Gorbunova - Eulerian spatiotemporal correlations in passive scalar turbulence</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gorbunova2021/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gorbunova2021/</guid><description>In this paper, Anastasiia Gorbunova and co-authors study spatio-temporal correlation function of a passive scalar in 3D homogeneous isotropic turbulence and synthetic velocity fields, by means of direct numerical simulations. Two regimes of temporal decorrelation are observed: a Gaussian at small time lags and exponential at large time lags. This behaviour is in agreement with recent analytical results.</description></item><item><title> GCM-Filters publication</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gcmfilter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gcmfilter/</guid><description>Ryan Abernathey, Arthur Guillaumin, Andrew Ross and Laure Zanna are co-authors of this article in JOSS presenting a new python package that allows scientists to perform spatial filtering analysis in an easy, flexible and efficient way. The package was initially developed as part of the Climate Process Team and will help further M²LInES goals of using data and ML to improve subgrid parameterizations.</description></item><item><title> Marika Holland - Arctic sea ice sensitivity to lateral melting representation</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/holland2022/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 08:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/holland2022/</guid><description>Marika Holland is a co-author in this research paper using a coupled climate model (CESM2.0) to assess the sensitivity of modeled sea ice state to the lateral melt parameterization, in preindustrial and 2×CO₂ runs.</description></item><item><title> Balaji - Are GCMs obsolete?</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/balaji2022/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 07:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/balaji2022/</guid><description>V Balaji and co-authors, including Julie Deshayes, describe in this paper the shortcomings of current GCMs and the methods in development to improve them. It is currently under review as a PNAS Perspective.</description></item><item><title> Adam Subel - Stable a posteriori LES of 2D turbulence using convolutional neural networks</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/220401subel/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/220401subel/</guid><description>Using 2D decaying turbulence as a testbed, this work, co-authored by Adam Subel, explores the importance of accurately capturing backscattering in generating stable online LES. Additionally, it shows that transfer learning can enable generalization to flows with a higher Reynolds number, even if an increase in resolution is needed.</description></item><item><title> Joan Bruna - Neural Galerkin Scheme preprint</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/220401bruna/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/220401bruna/</guid><description>Lead author Joan Bruna introduces in this preprint, a method to use deep neural network when training data are initially unavailable: Neural Galerkin schemes integrate time-dependent partial differential equations with deep networks by generating the data needed to advance their solution on-the-fly using importance sampling.</description></item><item><title> Mitch Bushuk on the Mechanisms of Regional Arctic Sea Ice Predictability</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/220401bushuk/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/220401bushuk/</guid><description>In this article, Mitch Bushuk and co-authors evaluate regional Arctic sea ice extent predictions made with the FLOR and SPEAR_MED dynamical seasonal forecast systems, and investigate the mechanisms of predictability in these systems. Feiyu Lu also contributed to the research.</description></item><item><title> Dhruv Balwada and Laure Zanna article in SIAM news</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/balwadazanna22/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/balwadazanna22/</guid><description>Dhruv Balwada and Laure Zanna published an article in SIAM news, detailing current insights on using Machine Learning for multiscale systems, particularly in the context of Climate prediction.</description></item><item><title>Movie about M²LInES and featured on AGU TV!</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/m2linesmovie/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/m2linesmovie/</guid><description>Check out the movie made about our project! It summarizes our goals and challenges and how we are planning to use Data and Machine Learning to address them.
A short version of the movie was featured on AGU TV (starting at 5:17):</description></item><item><title> Aakash Sane - Evaluating Coupled Climate Model Parameterizations</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/sanepaper2022/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/sanepaper2022/</guid><description>Aakash Sane is a co-author in this paper showing that ocean models having Langmuir turbulence and submesoscale restratification parameterizations give the most accurate simulation of monsoon intraseasonal oscillation events.</description></item><item><title> Book Chapter - Isopycnal mixing by Ryan Abernathey</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/abernatheychapter/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/abernatheychapter/</guid><description>In a new book chapter, Ryan Abernathey reviews both the frameworks to study isopycnal mixing and the recent insights gained from observations and simulations. This chapter lays the foundation on how isopycnal mixing is parametrized in ocean models.
Read the book chapter here</description></item><item><title>Climate-Invariant Machine Learning</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/beuclerpreprint/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/beuclerpreprint/</guid><description>Tom Beucler and co-authors demonstrate in this preprint, that physically rescaling the inputs and outputs of ML algorithms help them generalize to unseen climates and geographies. Janni Yuval, Paul O’Gorman and Pierre Gentine contributed to the research.</description></item><item><title>Deep Probability Estimation</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/fernandezgranda21/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/fernandezgranda21/</guid><description>Carlos Fernandez-Granda and co-authors, including Laure Zanna, investigate in this preprint, probability estimation from high-dimensional data using deep neural networks. In particular, they propose a new method for probability estimation, which outperforms existing approaches on simulated as well as on three real-world datasets (including climatology data).</description></item><item><title>Hugo Frezat - A posteriori learning of quasi-geostrophic turbulence parametrization</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/frezatpreprint/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/frezatpreprint/</guid><description>In this paper, Hugo Frezat, Julien Le Sommer, and their co-authors, train a NN-based closures for QG dynamics with an a posteriori learning criteria based on model integrations over several time-steps. While this strategy yields closures which outperform existing baselines, it requires the coarse resolution model to be differentiable in order to minimize the training loss.</description></item><item><title>Tropical precipitation clusters as islands on a rough water-vapor topography</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/ziweili21/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/ziweili21/</guid><description>Viewing precipitation clusters as islands on a rough column-water-vapor (CWV) topography, lead author Ziwei Li used self-affine theories to relate multiple scale-free statistics of precipitation clusters to the properties of CWV islands. Paul O’Gorman also contributed to the research. Read more.</description></item><item><title> AGU presentations by M²LInES team members</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/agupresentation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/agupresentation/</guid><description>Schedule of AGU presentations from team members Monday Dec 13th 12:53 CST Feiyu Lu “Prediction and Attribution of the Western North America heatwave in June-July of 2021”. Abstract
14:50 CST Will Chapman “Skillful Wintertime Temperature Forecasts out to 6 Weeks with Machine Learning Methods over the America&amp;rsquo;s”. Abstract
14:51 CST Janni Yuval “Neural-Network Parameterization of Subgrid Momentum Transport Learned from a High-Resolution Simulation”. Abstract</description></item><item><title> M²LInES Kickoff meeting</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/kickoffoct/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/kickoffoct/</guid><description>M²LInES Kickoff meeting on Oct 28th and 29th was tremendously successful! It gathered the team, including all our new and incoming hires, our funders, as well as the VESRI advisory board. It featured amazing talks and sparked insightful discussions. Thank you to all who joined us and thank you to our brilliant speakers: Laure Zanna, Pierre Gentine, Paul O’Gorman, Carlos Fernandez-Granda, Ryan Abernathey, Judith Berner and Alistair Adcroft.</description></item><item><title> The influence of snow on sea ice as assessed from simulations of CESM2 - Marika Holland</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/hollandetal/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/hollandetal/</guid><description>Lead author Marika Holland demonstrates in this paper the importance of accurately representing snow accumulation on sea-ice in coupled earth system models. Diagnosing snow and ice thickness heterogeneity will be a crucial part of the M²LInES project.</description></item><item><title> Probabilistic Predictions from Deterministic Atmospheric River Forecasts with Deep Learning - Will Chapman</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/chapmanetal/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/chapmanetal/</guid><description>In this paper, Will Chapman uses a deep learning (DL) based post-processing framework to generate probabilistic forecasts of atmospheric rivers from single member numerical weather prediction (NWP) forecasts. They show that the DL forecasts are reliable and sharp, and compete well with dynamically generated NWP ensembles.</description></item><item><title> Response of Northern Hemisphere Weather and Climate to Arctic Sea Ice Decline - Lorenzo Zampieri</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/zampierietal21/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/zampierietal21/</guid><description>Lorenzo Zampieri and his co-authors investigates in this study whether the simulated atmospheric midlatitude response to future changes in Arctic sea ice depends on the resolution of the atmospheric model.</description></item><item><title> UN AI for Good: AI and Climate Science seminars</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/aiforgood/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/aiforgood/</guid><description>UN AI for Good has announced their line up for their Fall/Winter Seminars. You can find the list of speakers for the AI and Climate Science seminars here.
In particular several M²LInES team members will be presenting on the following dates:
Paul O’Gorman - Nov 3rd Laure Zanna - Nov 10th. Pierre Gentine - Nov 17th</description></item><item><title>Adaptive Denoising via GainTuning - Carlos Fernandez-Granda</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/fernandezgranda/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/fernandezgranda/</guid><description>Carlos Fernandez-Granda and his team introduces a new technique for adaptive denoising of Deep convolutional neural networks. Available to read here as a preprint.</description></item><item><title>Impact of Sea-Ice Model Complexity on model performance by Lorenzo Zampieri</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/zampierijames/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/zampierijames/</guid><description>Incoming postdoc Lorenzo Zampieri demonstrates in this article how increased sea-ice model complexity can improve the simulated sea-ice concentration and snow thickness. Available to read in open access here.</description></item><item><title>Article by Dhruv Balwada et al. - Role of submesoscale flows on vertical fluxes</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/balwada-article/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/balwada-article/</guid><description>Dhruv Balwada is the lead author in this article analyzing the role of submesoscale flows on tracer fluxes. You can read it here (or in earthArXiv here). Ryan Abernathey also contributed to the research.</description></item><item><title>Estimating Ocean Surface Currents With Machine Learning - Ryan Abernathey</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/abernatheypaper/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/abernatheypaper/</guid><description>Ryan Abernathey is the senior author in this publication where deep learning models are trained to effectively “learn” spatial gradients and the physics of surface currents. You can read it here.</description></item><item><title>Seasonal Prediction and Predictability of Regional Antarctic Sea Ice - Mitch Bushuk</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/bushukarticle/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/bushukarticle/</guid><description>In this article, lead author Mitch Bushuk uses the forecast system that his team will be using for M²LInES. You can read it here (or in Researchgate here).</description></item><item><title>Neural Networks as Geometric Chaotic Maps - by Ziwei Li</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/ziweiliarticle/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/ziweiliarticle/</guid><description>M²LInES incoming postdoc Ziwei Li is the lead author on a new article on Neural Networks as Geometric Chaotic Maps. You can read it here (or in arXiv here).</description></item><item><title>Neural network parametrization of a subgrid process - by Janni Yuval and Paul O'Gorman</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/articleyuval/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/articleyuval/</guid><description>A new M²LInES scientific paper on Neural-network parameterization of subgrid momentum transport in the atmosphere, by members Janni Yuval and Paul O&amp;rsquo;Gorman, is available to read as a preprint here.</description></item><item><title> Article in Eos by Yuval et al. - Call for Papers on Machine Learning and Earth System Modeling</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/articlejamescall/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/articlejamescall/</guid><description>M²LInES members Janni Yuval is the lead author in this article inviting scientists to contribute to a new special collection in Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems (JAMES). The collection will focus on the use of new machine learning methodologies and applications of machine learning to Earth system modeling. Pierre Gentine and Laure Zanna are co-authors of the article.
Link to contribute to the special collection in JAMES here</description></item><item><title> Upcoming Seminar by Laure Zanna at One World Mathematics of Climate - 7/6</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/oneworld/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/oneworld/</guid><description>M²LInES lead PI Laure Zanna will give a seminar at the One World Mathematics of Climate on July 6th 12pm EST. She will talk about some of the machine learning work on ocean eddy parameterization and about the work being done at M²LInES. Tune in here</description></item><item><title> A Bayesian approach towards sea ice freeboard estimates - paper by Will Gregory</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/willgregorypaper/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/willgregorypaper/</guid><description>Incoming M²LInES postdoc Will Gregory is the lead author in this new publication on using a Bayesian approach towards sea ice freeboard estimates from satellite observations.
This work has 3 important implications: 1) a daily freeboard product allows them, for the first time, to assess radar freeboard (and ultimately sea ice thickness) variability on sub-weekly timescales &amp;ndash; it takes up to 1 month for each satellite to generate pan-Arctic coverage alone.</description></item><item><title> s2s challenge</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/s2schallenge/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 10:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/s2schallenge/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Judith Berner is setting up a team to participate to the s2s challenge, which goal is to improve sub-seasonal to seasonal predictions using AI. M²LInES postdocs Janni Yuval and Tarun Verma will also be part of the team. The deadline to register is July 1st 2021. More info here</description></item><item><title> KITP conference: Machine Learning for Climate</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/kitpconference/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 10:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/kitpconference/</guid><description>M²LInES Lead PI Laure Zanna is the co-director of the next conference on Machine Learning for Climate of the Kavli Institute for Theoretical Physics (KITP) . It will take place Nov 1-4 2021. Info and registration here</description></item><item><title> 2021 CESM workshop: M²LInES team members presenting on June 17th</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/cesmworkshop/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/cesmworkshop/</guid><description>M²LInES team members will present at Machine Learning session for the CESM workshop on June 17. Info and agenda here</description></item><item><title> Call for Papers for JAMES</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/5jamescall/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/5jamescall/</guid><description>M²LInES members Janni Yuval, Pierre Gentine and Laure Zanna are part of the organizers of a special collection at JAMES (Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems) that will include both new ML methodologies developed for advancing Earth system science and ML applications to Earth system modeling. Papers submissions are open. The community is invited to contribute. More information here</description></item><item><title>Using deep learning to emulate cloud superparameterization - new paper by PI Gentine</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/3gentinepaper1/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/3gentinepaper1/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Pierre Gentine is the senior author in this new publication on using deep learning for emulating cloud superparameterization in climate models. Research Scientist Tom Beucler is a co-author. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title> Neural Network emulating physical constraints - paper by PI Gentine</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/4gentinepaper2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/4gentinepaper2/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Pierre Gentine is the senior author and Research Scientist Tom Beucler is the lead author in this new publication on enforcing analytic constraints in Neural Networks emulating physical systems. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title> New paper on deep learning parametrization by Guillaumin and Zanna</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/1guillauminpaper/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/1guillauminpaper/</guid><description>In this paper, M²LInES postdoc Arthur Guillaumin and lead PI Laure Zanna developed a stochastic deep learning parametrization that is trained on high-resolution data from CM2.6, a coupled climate model. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title> Modelisation using neural network - paper by PI Le Sommer</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2jlesommerpaper/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2jlesommerpaper/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Julien Le Sommer is a co-author in this new publication using neural network to model subgrid-scale processes. Read their paper here</description></item></channel></rss>