<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>News on M²LInES</title><link>/news/</link><description>Recent content in News on M²LInES</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title> Article in Eos by Yuval et al. - Call for Papers on Machine Learning and Earth System Modeling</title><link>/news/articlejamescall/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/articlejamescall/</guid><description>M²LInES members Janni Yuval is the lead author in this article inviting scientists to contribute to a new special collection in Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems (JAMES). The collection will focus on the use of new machine learning methodologies and applications of machine learning to Earth system modeling. Pierre Gentine and Laure Zanna are co-authors of the article.
Link to contribute to the special collection in JAMES here</description></item><item><title> Upcoming Seminar by Laure Zanna at One World Mathematics of Climate - 7/6</title><link>/news/oneworld/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/oneworld/</guid><description>M²LInES lead PI Laure Zanna will give a seminar at the One World Mathematics of Climate on July 6th 12pm EST. She will talk about some of the machine learning work on ocean eddy parameterization and about the work being done at M²LInES. Tune in here</description></item><item><title> M²LInES-related paper by postdoc Will Gregory</title><link>/news/willpaper/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/willpaper/</guid><description>Incoming M²LInES postdoc Will Gregory is the lead author in this new publication.
This work has 3 important implications: 1) a daily freeboard product allows them, for the first time, to assess radar freeboard (and ultimately sea ice thickness) variability on sub-weekly timescales &amp;ndash; it takes up to 1 month for each satellite to generate pan-Arctic coverage alone. 2) The method allows them to derive estimates of radar freeboard correlation length scales, which together with the daily freeboards, could be useful in sea ice data assimilation systems.</description></item><item><title> s2s challenge</title><link>/news/s2schallenge/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 10:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/s2schallenge/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Judith Berner is setting up a team to participate to the s2s challenge, which goal is to improve sub-seasonal to seasonal predictions using AI. M²LInES postdocs Janni Yuval and Tarun Verma will also be part of the team. The deadline to register is July 1st 2021. More info here</description></item><item><title> KITP conference: Machine Learning for Climate</title><link>/news/kitpconference/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 10:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/kitpconference/</guid><description>M²LInES Lead PI Laure Zanna is the co-director of the next conference on Machine Learning for Climate of the Kavli Institute for Theoretical Physics (KITP) . It will take place Nov 1-4 2021. Info and registration here</description></item><item><title> 2021 CESM workshop: M²LInES team members presenting on June 17th</title><link>/news/cesmworkshop/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/cesmworkshop/</guid><description>M²LInES team members will present at Machine Learning session for the CESM workshop on June 17. Info and agenda here</description></item><item><title> Call for Papers for JAMES</title><link>/news/5jamescall/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/5jamescall/</guid><description>M²LInES members Janni Yuval, Pierre Gentine and Laure Zanna are part of the organizers of a special collection at JAMES (Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems) that will include both new ML methodologies developed for advancing Earth system science and ML applications to Earth system modeling. Papers submissions are open. The community is invited to contribute. More information here</description></item><item><title>M²LInES-related paper by PI Gentine</title><link>/news/3pierrepaper1/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/3pierrepaper1/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Pierre Gentine is the senior author in this new publication. Research Scientist Tom Beucler is a co-author. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title> M²LInES-related paper by PI Gentine</title><link>/news/4pierrepaper2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/4pierrepaper2/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Pierre Gentine is the senior author and Research Scientist Tom Beucler is the lead author in this new publication. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title> New paper by M²LInES members Guillaumin and Zanna</title><link>/news/1arthurpaper/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/1arthurpaper/</guid><description>In this paper, M²LInES postdoc Arthur Guillaumin and lead PI Laure Zanna developed a stochastic deep learning parametrization that is trained on high-resolution data from CM2.6, a coupled climate model. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title> M²LInES-related paper by PI Le Sommer</title><link>/news/2julienpaper/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/2julienpaper/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Julien Le Sommer is a co-author in this new publication. Read their paper here</description></item></channel></rss>