<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>News on M²LInES</title><link>/news/</link><description>Recent content in News on M²LInES</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 09:29:16 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title> M²LInES Kickoff meeting</title><link>/news/kickoffoct/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/kickoffoct/</guid><description>M²LInES Kickoff meeting on Oct 28th and 29th was tremendously successful! It gathered the team, including all our new and incoming hires, our funders, as well as the VESRI advisory board. It featured amazing talks and sparked insightful discussions. Thank you to all who joined us and thank you to our brilliant speakers: Laure Zanna, Pierre Gentine, Paul O’Gorman, Carlos Fernandez-Granda, Ryan Abernathey, Judith Berner and Alistair Adcroft.</description></item><item><title> The influence of snow on sea ice as assessed from simulations of CESM2 - Marika Holland</title><link>/news/hollandetal/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/hollandetal/</guid><description>Lead author Marika Holland demonstrates in this paper the importance of accurately representing snow accumulation on sea-ice in coupled earth system models. Diagnosing snow and ice thickness heterogeneity will be a crucial part of the M²LInES project.</description></item><item><title> Probabilistic Predictions from Deterministic Atmospheric River Forecasts with Deep Learning - Will Chapman</title><link>/news/chapmanetal/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/chapmanetal/</guid><description>In this paper, Will Chapman uses a deep learning (DL) based post-processing framework to generate probabilistic forecasts of atmospheric rivers from single member numerical weather prediction (NWP) forecasts. They show that the DL forecasts are reliable and sharp, and compete well with dynamically generated NWP ensembles.</description></item><item><title> Response of Northern Hemisphere Weather and Climate to Arctic Sea Ice Decline - Lorenzo Zampieri</title><link>/news/zampierietal21/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/zampierietal21/</guid><description>Lorenzo Zampieri and his co-authors investigates in this study whether the simulated atmospheric midlatitude response to future changes in Arctic sea ice depends on the resolution of the atmospheric model.</description></item><item><title> UN AI for Good: AI and Climate Science seminars</title><link>/news/aiforgood/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/aiforgood/</guid><description>UN AI for Good has announced their line up for their Fall/Winter Seminars. You can find the list of speakers for the AI and Climate Science seminars here.
In particular several M²LInES team members will be presenting on the following dates:
Paul O’Gorman - Nov 3rd Laure Zanna - Nov 10th. Pierre Gentine - Nov 17th</description></item><item><title>Adaptive Denoising via GainTuning - Carlos Fernandez-Granda</title><link>/news/fernandezgranda/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/fernandezgranda/</guid><description>Carlos Fernandez-Granda and his team introduces a new technique for adaptive denoising of Deep convolutional neural networks. Available to read here as a preprint.</description></item><item><title>Impact of Sea-Ice Model Complexity on model performance by Lorenzo Zampieri</title><link>/news/zampierijames/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/zampierijames/</guid><description>Incoming postdoc Lorenzo Zampieri demonstrates in this article how increased sea-ice model complexity can improve the simulated sea-ice concentration and snow thickness. Available to read in open access here.</description></item><item><title>Article by Dhruv Balwada et al. - Role of submesoscale flows on vertical fluxes</title><link>/news/balwada-article/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/balwada-article/</guid><description>Dhruv Balwada is the lead author in this article analyzing the role of submesoscale flows on tracer fluxes. You can read it here (or in earthArXiv here). Ryan Abernathey also contributed to the research.</description></item><item><title>Estimating Ocean Surface Currents With Machine Learning - Ryan Abernathey</title><link>/news/abernatheypaper/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/abernatheypaper/</guid><description>Ryan Abernathey is the senior author in this publication where deep learning models are trained to effectively “learn” spatial gradients and the physics of surface currents. You can read it here.</description></item><item><title>Seasonal Prediction and Predictability of Regional Antarctic Sea Ice - Mitch Bushuk</title><link>/news/bushukarticle/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/bushukarticle/</guid><description>In this article, lead author Mitch Bushuk uses the forecast system that his team will be using for M²LInES. You can read it here (or in Researchgate here).</description></item><item><title>Neural Networks as Geometric Chaotic Maps - by Ziwei Li</title><link>/news/ziweiliarticle/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/ziweiliarticle/</guid><description>M²LInES incoming postdoc Ziwei Li is the lead author on a new article on Neural Networks as Geometric Chaotic Maps. You can read it here (or in arXiv here).</description></item><item><title>Neural network parametrization of a subgrid process - by Janni Yuval and Paul O'Gorman</title><link>/news/articleyuval/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/articleyuval/</guid><description>A new M²LInES scientific paper on Neural-network parameterization of subgrid momentum transport in the atmosphere, by members Janni Yuval and Paul O&amp;rsquo;Gorman, is available to read as a preprint here.</description></item><item><title> Article in Eos by Yuval et al. - Call for Papers on Machine Learning and Earth System Modeling</title><link>/news/articlejamescall/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/articlejamescall/</guid><description>M²LInES members Janni Yuval is the lead author in this article inviting scientists to contribute to a new special collection in Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems (JAMES). The collection will focus on the use of new machine learning methodologies and applications of machine learning to Earth system modeling. Pierre Gentine and Laure Zanna are co-authors of the article.
Link to contribute to the special collection in JAMES here</description></item><item><title> Upcoming Seminar by Laure Zanna at One World Mathematics of Climate - 7/6</title><link>/news/oneworld/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/oneworld/</guid><description>M²LInES lead PI Laure Zanna will give a seminar at the One World Mathematics of Climate on July 6th 12pm EST. She will talk about some of the machine learning work on ocean eddy parameterization and about the work being done at M²LInES. Tune in here</description></item><item><title> A Bayesian approach towards sea ice freeboard estimates - paper by Will Gregory</title><link>/news/willgregorypaper/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/willgregorypaper/</guid><description>Incoming M²LInES postdoc Will Gregory is the lead author in this new publication on using a Bayesian approach towards sea ice freeboard estimates from satellite observations.
This work has 3 important implications: 1) a daily freeboard product allows them, for the first time, to assess radar freeboard (and ultimately sea ice thickness) variability on sub-weekly timescales &amp;ndash; it takes up to 1 month for each satellite to generate pan-Arctic coverage alone.</description></item><item><title> s2s challenge</title><link>/news/s2schallenge/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 10:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/s2schallenge/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Judith Berner is setting up a team to participate to the s2s challenge, which goal is to improve sub-seasonal to seasonal predictions using AI. M²LInES postdocs Janni Yuval and Tarun Verma will also be part of the team. The deadline to register is July 1st 2021. More info here</description></item><item><title> KITP conference: Machine Learning for Climate</title><link>/news/kitpconference/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 10:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/kitpconference/</guid><description>M²LInES Lead PI Laure Zanna is the co-director of the next conference on Machine Learning for Climate of the Kavli Institute for Theoretical Physics (KITP) . It will take place Nov 1-4 2021. Info and registration here</description></item><item><title> 2021 CESM workshop: M²LInES team members presenting on June 17th</title><link>/news/cesmworkshop/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/cesmworkshop/</guid><description>M²LInES team members will present at Machine Learning session for the CESM workshop on June 17. Info and agenda here</description></item><item><title> Call for Papers for JAMES</title><link>/news/5jamescall/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/5jamescall/</guid><description>M²LInES members Janni Yuval, Pierre Gentine and Laure Zanna are part of the organizers of a special collection at JAMES (Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems) that will include both new ML methodologies developed for advancing Earth system science and ML applications to Earth system modeling. Papers submissions are open. The community is invited to contribute. More information here</description></item><item><title>Using deep learning to emulate cloud superparameterization - new paper by PI Gentine</title><link>/news/3gentinepaper1/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/3gentinepaper1/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Pierre Gentine is the senior author in this new publication on using deep learning for emulating cloud superparameterization in climate models. Research Scientist Tom Beucler is a co-author. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title> Neural Network emulating physical constraints - paper by PI Gentine</title><link>/news/4gentinepaper2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/4gentinepaper2/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Pierre Gentine is the senior author and Research Scientist Tom Beucler is the lead author in this new publication on enforcing analytic constraints in Neural Networks emulating physical systems. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title> New paper on deep learning parametrization by Guillaumin and Zanna</title><link>/news/1guillauminpaper/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/1guillauminpaper/</guid><description>In this paper, M²LInES postdoc Arthur Guillaumin and lead PI Laure Zanna developed a stochastic deep learning parametrization that is trained on high-resolution data from CM2.6, a coupled climate model. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title> Modelisation using neural network - paper by PI Le Sommer</title><link>/news/2jlesommerpaper/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>/news/2jlesommerpaper/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Julien Le Sommer is a co-author in this new publication using neural network to model subgrid-scale processes. Read their paper here</description></item></channel></rss>