<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>News on M²LInES</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/</link><description>Recent content in News on M²LInES</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 09:29:16 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://m2lines.github.io/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Atmosphere connected supermodel linking CAM5 and CAM6</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2510chapman/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2510chapman/</guid><description>Led by Will Chapman, this paper presents the first atmosphere connected supermodel linking CAM5 and CAM6, which exchange information interactively to form a new dynamical system. In tests of a single untrained supermodel, the models synchronize well across timescales and preserve storm track variability even for variables without direct information exchange. Synchronization is weaker in the tropics, but key large scale patterns such as the North Atlantic Oscillation and Pacific North American Pattern remain intact, and for some variables mean biases are reduced compared to the individual models.</description></item><item><title>CERA: A Framework for Improved Generalization of Machine Learning Models to Changed Climates</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2510shuchang/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2510shuchang/</guid><description>Shuchang Liu and Paul O’Gorman introduce CERA , a machine learning framework designed to improve the generalizability of ML-models under climate change. CERA uses an autoencoder with latent space alignment followed by a predictor to estimate moist physics processes. Trained only on control climate data with additional unlabeled warmer climate inputs, it improves predictions in a +4 K climate and outperforms both raw input and physics informed baselines. CERA captures shifts in precipitation extremes and the structure of moisture tendencies while reducing the need for manual climate invariant feature engineering, offering promise for hybrid ML physics systems and applications such as statistical downscaling.</description></item><item><title>SamudrACE</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2510samudrace/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2510samudrace/</guid><description>In a collaboration between M²LInES and AI2, researchers present SamudrACE , a machine learning based global climate model emulator. SamudrACE couples 3D atmosphere, 3D ocean, sea ice and land surface emulators to simulate centuries of climate at 1-degree horizontal resolution with 6-hourly atmospheric and 5-daily oceanic output. It produces 145 2D fields across multiple vertical levels with realistic variability in key climate phenomena such as ENSO. The model remains highly stable and shows low climate biases comparable to its individual components while capturing coupled climate behavior that uncoupled models cannot reproduce.</description></item><item><title>Data-driven parameterization for mesoscale thickness fluxes</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2509balwada/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2509balwada/</guid><description>This study , led by Dhruv Balwada, introduces a new data-driven parameterization to better represent how mesoscale eddies remove potential energy from the ocean in climate models. Unlike the widely used Gent-McWilliams (GM) scheme, which can hinder resolved eddies and lacks a robust basis for tuning, this approach is both flow-aware and scale-aware, minimizing negative impacts on resolved dynamics. Built with a lightweight neural network, the method is efficient, easy to implement, and successfully tested in NOAA’s MOM6 model.</description></item><item><title>Plug-and-Play Data Assimilation</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2509yongquan/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2509yongquan/</guid><description>Led by Yongquan Qu, this study presents PnP-DA (Plug-and-Play Data Assimilation), a new method to improve forecasts in Earth system models. As part of the LEAP project, the team combines lightweight analysis updates with a pretrained generative prior to overcome the limitations of traditional approaches that assume overly simple error statistics. Tests on chaotic systems show that it consistently reduces forecast errors across a range of conditions, outperforming classical data assimilation methods.</description></item><item><title>M²LInES AI Ocean Emulator, Samudra, is now included in the Ai2 ACE codebase</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2508ai2samudra/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2508ai2samudra/</guid><description>The Ai2 Climate Modeling team has released a new version of their climate emulator. In this latest release , Samudra, the AI global ocean emulator developed by M²LInES, is now integrated into Ai2&amp;rsquo;s full model framework. We encourage you to check out the Ai2 codebase and Samudra&amp;rsquo;s original code to create your own ocean simulations.</description></item><item><title>Neural models of multiscale systems</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2508falasca/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2508falasca/</guid><description>This study examines fundamental challenges in using data-driven models, especially neural networks, for simulating complex climate dynamics. While these models can often reproduce average climate behavior, they struggle to capture responses to external changes. The author, Fabrizio Falasca, shows that this limitation becomes especially pronounced when only partial observations are available, a common scenario in real-world climate systems. His findings highlight the importance of incorporating physically informed methods, like coarse-graining and stochastic parameterizations, to improve the accuracy and interpretability of neural climate emulators.</description></item><item><title>The Impact of Sub-Grid Heterogeneity on Air-Sea Turbulent Heat Flux in Coupled Climate Models</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2508balwada/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2508balwada/</guid><description>A new paper , led by Julius Busecke and Dhruv Balwada, highlights how small-scale air-sea interactions, often unresolved in climate models, can significantly influence large-scale heat exchange between the ocean and atmosphere. Using high-resolution coupled simulations, researchers found that this small-scale variability leads to a systematic global ocean cooling of about 4 W/m², with regional effects up to 100 W/m². These findings underscore the critical role of atmospheric wind and ocean temperature heterogeneity, offering new insights for improving climate model accuracy.</description></item><item><title>Advancing global sea ice prediction capabilities</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2507gregory/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2507gregory/</guid><description>Gregory et al. present in this preprint , a hybrid modeling approach that integrates machine learning (ML) into the GFDL SPEAR climate model to correct sea ice biases in real time. Two versions are tested: one that includes coupled feedbacks (HybridCPL) and one that does not (HybridIO). HybridCPL significantly improves Arctic and Antarctic sea ice forecasts on seasonal and subseasonal timescales. In contrast, HybridIO performs poorly due to unanticipated feedbacks. These results highlight the importance of training ML models within coupled climate systems for reliable predictions.</description></item><item><title>Carlos Fernandez-Granda new book</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2507carlos/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2507carlos/</guid><description>Carlos Fernandez-Granda new book is out! Published by Cambridge University Press , the book is a self-contained guide to the two pillars of data science, probability theory, and statistics. The materials, which include 200 exercises with solutions, 102 Python notebooks using 23 real-world datasets, 115 YouTube videos with slides, and a free preprint, can be found at this website .</description></item><item><title>Community Research Earth Digital Intelligence Twin</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2507credit/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2507credit/</guid><description>A new framework from NCAR, called CREDIT (Community Research Earth Digital Intelligence Twin), is making it easier for researchers to develop and test AI-based weather prediction models. Introduced in this paper , CREDIT supports flexible model design and training, helping address key challenges in AI-based forecasting. Using this platform, researchers introduced WXFormer, a novel model that outperforms traditional forecasting systems like ECMWF’s IFS on 10-day forecasts, while being much more computationally efficient.</description></item><item><title>Parameterization of mesoscale eddies</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2507perezhogin/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2507perezhogin/</guid><description>Perezhogin et al. propose in this preprint , a physics-informed neural network to improve the generalization of data-driven mesoscale eddy parameterizations in ocean models. By applying local input-output scaling based on dimensional analysis, their method adapts to different grid resolutions and depths. This approach enhances energy representation and affects biases in both idealized and global ocean simulations. The scaling framework is broadly applicable and robust across configurations. Results show competitive performance compared to traditional parameterizations.</description></item><item><title>Samudra and Laure Zanna featured in APS news article!</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2507samudra/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2507samudra/</guid><description>This APS news article highlights how AI is reshaping climate science, offering faster, smarter ways to model Earth’s complex systems. It features highlights from the Global Physics Summit, where researchers presented how machine learning is accelerating simulations, uncovering new physics, and helping build more precise climate models, all while keeping physics at the core. In particular, it spotlights interview exerts with Laure Zanna presenting Samudra , the M²LInES created AI emulator.</description></item><item><title>Regional multi-year predictability of Antarctic sea ice in CESM2 and its implications for marine ecosystems</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2504holland/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2504holland/</guid><description>This new article explores the predictability of Antarctic sea ice, which varies by region and is influenced by ocean and atmospheric conditions. Using climate models, Marika Holland and co-authors, confirm that sea ice changes can be predicted months in advance, with cycles of predictability linked to ice growth and retreat: it remains predictable during growth, loses predictability when melting, and regains it as it reforms. Ocean temperature patterns near the ice edge play a key role, with variations across different regions.</description></item><item><title>The futures of climate modeling</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2504zanna/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2504zanna/</guid><description>New tools like kilometer-scale modeling, parameter tuning, and AI/machine learning are reshaping the climate modeling field, sparking debate on the best path forward. Five internationally renowned female climate scientists, including Laure Zanna, sign this perspective piece in Nature climate and atmospheric science. Their analysis draws lessons from past research to guide the future of climate modeling. The conclusion: the future of climate modeling depends on embracing diverse tools and methodologies to drive meaningful progress!</description></item><item><title>Thermalizer: Stable autoregressive neural emulation of spatiotemporal chaos</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2504pedersen/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2504pedersen/</guid><description>Autoregressive surrogate models (emulators) make fast predictions for dynamical systems but become unstable over time due to error buildup. This study , led by Chris Pedersen, introduces thermalization, a technique leveraging diffusion models to adaptively correct errors during inference. By stabilizing predictions, it extends emulated rollouts of chaotic and turbulent systems by several orders of magnitude. This breakthrough application of diffusion models enhances the utility of emulators, and can be applied to autoregressive models across science and engineering.</description></item><item><title>Deep Learning Turbulence Closures Generalize Best With Physics-based Methods</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2503connolly/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2503connolly/</guid><description>Representing atmospheric turbulence in climate models requires estimating unresolved small-scale forces. This study , led by Alex Connolly, uses a deep neural network (DNN) to improve turbulence modeling by predicting these forces in large-eddy simulations (LES) of the atmospheric boundary layer. The DNN is trained on high-resolution data and tested across different conditions. Results show that models using physics-based scaling perform better than those relying only on statistical normalization. Embedding physical symmetries into the model further improves accuracy.</description></item><item><title>Learning Propagators for Sea Surface Height Forecasts Using Koopman Autoencoders</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2503brettin/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2503brettin/</guid><description>Sea surface height forecasts are influenced by many uncertainties. Traditional statistical methods help make predictions but often rely on assumptions that don’t fully capture the climate system&amp;rsquo;s complexity. In this paper , Andrew Brettin and co-authors develop a machine learning model that learns a simplified representation of the climate system, improving sea surface height predictions. Their approach outperforms methods that separate data compression and prediction. Additionally, the model highlights key regions where better sea level representation can enhance regional forecasts.</description></item><item><title>Learning Machine Learning with Lorenz-96</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2502jupyterbook/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2502jupyterbook/</guid><description>Photo (credit: Will Chapman): students at the Future Earth Research School on data driven modeling using the M²LInES book for their group project!
The M²LInES team is proud to share this article and Jupyter Book published in the Journal of Open Science Education (JOSE) and led by Dhruv Balwada. Developed by our team, it aims to introduce Machine Learning (ML) methods to climate scientists and also climate modeling to machine learning experts.</description></item><item><title>New study addressing artifacts near coastlines caused by out-of-sample predictions</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2502zhang/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2502zhang/</guid><description>This study , led by Cheng Zhang, improves machine-learned models for simulating ocean mesoscale eddies by addressing artifacts near coastlines caused by out-of-sample predictions using convolutional neural networks (CNN). Comparing two different strategies for treating Boundary Conditions (BCs) in CNN models - zero and replicate padding - they show that replicate padding significantly reduces these artifacts, enhancing the accuracy and stability of ocean modeling near complex coastal regions.</description></item><item><title>Youtube channel to learn data science with M²LInES Carlos Fernandez Granda</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2502ytcarlos/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2502ytcarlos/</guid><description>If you are looking for clear material to understand statistics, probabilities, and mathematical tools for data science, check out the Youtube Channel of Carlos Fernandez-Granda where he shares recordings of his lectures at NYU!</description></item><item><title>Meet “Samudra”: M²LInES’ AI Global Ocean Emulator for Climate</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2412samudra/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2412samudra/</guid><description>Introducing Samudra: a unique neural network global ocean emulator for climate! Named after the Sanskrit word for &amp;lsquo;ocean,&amp;rsquo; Samudra is the first-of-its-kind 3D ocean climate emulator. It operates 150x faster than the original model and can run stably for centuries—all on a single A100 GPU. Dive into our blog post and article to learn more about this innovative advance in climate modeling!</description></item><item><title>M²LInES at AGU</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2412agu/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2412agu/</guid><description>Find all the posters and talks from our team at the AGU 24 conference in our December newsletter . If you are going, make sure to add them to your schedule.</description></item><item><title>Assessing the representation of Arctic sea ice and the marginal ice zone in ocean–sea ice reanalyses</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2411zampieri/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2411zampieri/</guid><description>Lorenzo Zampieri contributed to a new paper , published in the Cryosphere and led by Francesco Cocetta at the CMCC Foundation, where the representation of Arctic sea ice in ocean and sea ice reanalyses is evaluated against observations from different sources. In the upcoming years, these reanalyses will play an important role when used as training datasets from data-driven models of sea ice, which motivates evaluation studies such as this one.</description></item><item><title>The Emerging Human Influence on the Seasonal Cycle of Sea Surface Temperature</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2411shi/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2411shi/</guid><description>In this paper , Jia-Rui Shi and co-authors present scientific evidence indicating that a human-caused signal has already emerged in the seasonal cycle amplitude of Sea Surface Temperature (SST), distinct from the background noise of natural variability. The geographical patterns of the forced SST seasonal cycle change reveal two notable features: an increase in mid-latitudes of the Northern Hemisphere, which is associated with alterations in mixed-layer depth, and a robust dipole pattern in the Southern Hemisphere mid-latitudes, primarily driven by changes in surface winds.</description></item><item><title>Neural general circulation models for weather and climate</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2410yuval/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2410yuval/</guid><description>General circulation models (GCMs) are essential for weather and climate prediction. They use physics-based simulations to model large-scale dynamics and small-scale processes. Recently, machine-learning models have matched or exceeded GCMs in weather forecasting accuracy, but struggled with long-term stability and ensemble forecasts. In this Nature paper , co-led by Janni Yuval, a new model, NeuralGCM, integrates machine learning with a differentiable solver for atmospheric dynamics. It performs as well as top machine-learning and physics-based methods for short-term forecasts and can track climate metrics accurately for decades with prescribed sea surface temperature.</description></item><item><title>Distilling Machine Learning’s Added Value</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2410shamekh/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2410shamekh/</guid><description>This project addresses the challenge of explaining the added value of machine learning in weather and climate models, particularly for complex deep learning models. By constructing a hierarchy of Pareto-optimal models along an error-complexity plane, the researchers, including Sara Shamekh, provide insights into model development and performance. Through three applications—cloud cover parameterization, shortwave radiative transfer, and tropical precipitation modeling—it demonstrates how machine learning can uncover nonlinear relationships, improve parameterization, and capture key physical processes.</description></item><item><title>Pushing the frontiers in climate modelling and analysis with machine learning</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2409gentine/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2409gentine/</guid><description>This Nature Climate Change review, explores how machine learning can revolutionize climate modeling and analysis to meet growing demands for better projections and actionable climate information. The authors argue that now is the time to advance beyond current techniques by developing more accurate machine-learning-based Earth system models and creating new tools for predicting extreme events, improving detection methods, and enhancing climate model analysis. The review emphasizes the importance of collaboration between machine learning experts and climate scientists, along with the involvement of the private sector, to drive innovation and progress in climate science.</description></item><item><title>Scalable interpolation of satellite altimetry data with probabilistic machine learning</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2409gregory/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2409gregory/</guid><description>In this study , Will Gregory and co-authors developed an open-source Python library for interpolating sparse altimetry data, using local Gaussian process models. The library allows them to generate full images of daily sea ice fields at high spatial resolution (5 km), which they hypothesize could be used to train ML models for sub-grid scale parameterizations.</description></item><item><title>Constraints imply limited future weakening of AMOC</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2408bonan/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2408bonan/</guid><description>Climate models show varied predictions for the weakening of the Atlantic meridional overturning circulation (AMOC) this century. Researchers, including Laure Zanna and CliMA members, reduced this uncertainty by linking AMOC strength to the meridional density difference and overturning depth. They found that models with a deeper present-day overturning predict greater weakening due to less stratified North Atlantic waters. Using observational data, they estimate a modest AMOC weakening of about 4 Sv by century&amp;rsquo;s end, regardless of emissions.</description></item><item><title>Bringing Statistics to Storylines!</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2408gorman/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2408gorman/</guid><description>Accurately modeling extreme weather events is a major goal in climate science and weather risk management. High-resolution computational models provide precise data but are costly for capturing rare events. This study focuses on localized, short-lived events like heavy precipitation. The researchers, including Paul O’Gorman, developed a more efficient method for sampling these events by combining adaptive multilevel splitting (AMS) and “ensemble boosting.” The new approach, tested on the Lorenz-96 model, improved the sampling of extreme events by a factor of 10.</description></item><item><title>Sampling Hybrid Climate Simulation at Scale</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2407gentine/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2407gentine/</guid><description>Machine-learning (ML) models could enhance climate simulations by accurately representing small-scale processes like turbulence and convection. However, it&amp;rsquo;s unclear if better standalone (offline) performance leads to better integrated (online) performance in climate models. In this preprint, researchers, including Pierre Gentine, conducted extensive experiments with 2,970 hybrid simulations, finding that reducing offline error generally improves online accuracy, but some decisions can destabilize the model. Key improvements include incorporating memory, training on diverse climates, converting moisture input to relative humidity, and avoiding certain error metrics.</description></item><item><title>Improved Equatorial Upper Ocean Vertical Mixing</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2407reichl/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2407reichl/</guid><description>Deficiencies in how upper ocean mixing is modeled cause biases in climate simulations, affecting ocean heat uptake and ENSO predictions. To address this, researchers evaluated different mixing models, To address this, researchers evaluated different mixing models, in this study led by Brandon Reichl, using detailed simulations and applied improvements to NOAA/GFDL&amp;rsquo;s OM4 ocean model. Enhancements to the model&amp;rsquo;s mixing were informed by observational data and led to more accurate diurnal mixing, ocean currents, and upper ocean temperature profiles.</description></item><item><title>Transfer Learning for Emulating Ocean Climate Variability</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2406dheeshjith/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2406dheeshjith/</guid><description>We are adding the link to the preprint which is now accepted in ICML 2024 workshop and will be presented as a talk and a poster this week in Vienna: Link to the paper .
This study, led jointly by Surya Dheeshjith and Adam Subel, showcases Machine Learning Ocean Emulators accurately predicting global ocean surface conditions over 5-8 years under different CO₂ forcing scenarios. While the models struggle to generalize, fine-tuning with small amounts of additional data from warner climates can significantly improve model performance.</description></item><item><title>Data-driven dimensionality reduction and causal inference for spatiotemporal climate fields</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2406falasca/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2406falasca/</guid><description>One of the main challenges in statistical inference is to infer causal relations rather than simple correlations. In this paper , Fabrizio Falasca, Pavel Perezhogin, and Laure Zanna, propose a framework, based on linear response theory, to investigate and diagnose causal mechanisms in the climate system directly from data. The method is physically-based and scales to high-dimensional systems. Possible future applications include the response of the climate system to external perturbations and evaluate climate models outputs.</description></item><item><title>FTORCH and FORPY libraries now integrated to CESM!</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2405chapman/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2405chapman/</guid><description>The M²LInES team, assisted by Jack Atkinson (ICCS) and NCAR software engineers, have integrated the FTORCH and FORPY libraries for machine learning into CESM2.1.5. To set up a machine learning-enabled CESM instance on NCAR machines, follow the steps outlined in this repository . Contact Will Chapman for questions!</description></item><item><title>Predicting September Arctic Sea Ice</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2405bushuk/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2405bushuk/</guid><description>This study , led by Mitch Bushuk, provides a comparison of September Arctic sea ice seasonal prediction skill across a diverse set of 34 dynamical and statistical prediction models, quantifying the state-of-the-art in the rapidly growing sea ice prediction research community. The authors find that both dynamical and statistical prediction models can skillfully predict September Arctic sea ice 0–3 months in advance on Pan-Arctic, regional, and local spatial scales. These results demonstrate that there are bright prospects for skillful operational seasonal predictions of Arctic sea ice and highlight a number of crucial prediction system design aspects to guide future improvements.</description></item><item><title>Advances in Machine Learning Techniques for Sea Ice Applications</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2404zampieri/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2404zampieri/</guid><description>Forty-two international researchers, including Lorenzo Zampieri, were invited to Gwangmyeong (South Korea) to discuss recent advances in sea ice modelling to help guide the development of a state-of-the-art Korean sea ice modelling program under the leadership of the Korean Polar Research Institute (KOPRI). The workshop produced a report , which highlights 1) the opportunity to use AI techniques in support of various sea ice modelling tasks both for short-term and climate predictions and 2) the need for strengthened collaborations among international groups to connect existing “research bubbles” and facilitate the dissemination of ideas.</description></item><item><title>Joint Parameter and Parameterization Inference</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2404qu/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2404qu/</guid><description>In this article , Yongquan Qu, Mohamed Aziz Bhouri, and Pierre Gentine, tackle the joint inference and uncertainty quantification of poorly known physical parameters and machine learning parametrizations, for sub-grid scale dynamics. Achieved through a Bayesian framework enabled by differentiable programming, this method not only offers accurate parameter estimates, but also enables skillful forecasting, each accompanied by quantified uncertainty. This work is accepted at the ICLR 2024 Workshop on AI4Differential Equations In Science.</description></item><item><title>Building Ocean Climate Emulators</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2404adam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2404adam/</guid><description>AI can accelerate climate modeling by generating computationally cheap emulators of existing simulations. The design of climate emulators is an exciting and open challenge in AI+Climate. In this work , PhD student Adam Subel and Laure Zanna focus on two fundamental questions to facilitate the creation of ocean emulators: 1) the role of the atmosphere in improving the decadal skill of the emulator and 2) the representation of variables with distinct timescales (e.</description></item><item><title>Stress-testing the coupled behavior of hybrid physics-machine simulations</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2402bhouri/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2402bhouri/</guid><description>Machine Learning (ML)-based parameterizations of atmospheric convection have long been hailed as a promising alternative, with the potential to yield higher accuracy at a fraction of the cost of more explicit simulations. This work , co-authored by Mohamed Aziz Bhouri, investigates the coupled out-of-distribution extrapolation capabilities in &amp;ldquo;online&amp;rdquo; testing of different ML-based parameterization designs of atmospheric convection. Their results show that these design decisions are not enough to obtain satisfactory generalization benefits.</description></item><item><title>Stochastic Optimal Control Matching by Joan</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2402joan/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2402joan/</guid><description>Joan Bruna is a co-author in this preprint , introducing Stochastic Optimal Control Matching (SOCM), a novel Iterative Diffusion Optimization (IDO) technique for stochastic optimal control. Stochastic optimal control’s goal is to drive the behavior of noisy systems. In this work, the control is learned via a least squares problem by trying to fit a matching vector field. The key idea underlying SOCM is the path-wise reparameterization trick, a novel technique that is of independent interest, e.</description></item><item><title>Restratification Effect of Mesoscale Eddies</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2402nora/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2402nora/</guid><description>Nora Loose is lead author of this new paper - part of the Climate Process Team funded by NSF and NOAA - which compares two parameterizations (“GM90” and “GL90”) for the restratification effect of mesoscale eddies. The authors conclude that the less commonly used GL90 parameterization is a promising alternative to the popular GM90 scheme for isopycnal coordinate models, where it is more consistent with theory, computationally more efficient, easier to implement, and numerically more stable.</description></item><item><title>Data-driven equation discovery ocean model</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2401pavel/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2401pavel/</guid><description>Pavel Perezhogin is lead author of this new M²LInES preprint , describing the implementation, in the GFDL MOM6 ocean model, of a data-driven equation-discovery parameterization of mesoscale eddies. This scale-aware parametrization improved biases in the mean flow and energetics for a range of resolutions and in different ocean configurations. The work was done in collaboration with Cheng Zhang, Alistair Adcroft, Carlos Fernandez-Granda and Laure Zanna.</description></item><item><title>Learning Machine Learning with Lorenz-96</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2401l96/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2401l96/</guid><description>The M²LInES team is proud to share our Jupyter Book on Learning Machine Learning with Lorenz-96 . This educational tool provides a computationally accessible framework to understand how machine learning techniques can tackle climate science problems, including emulators, parameterizations, data assimilation, and uncertainty quantification. It is for all climate scientists wanting to learn or test machine learning algorithms or for machine learning experts to learn about climate modeling or develop new algorithms.</description></item><item><title>ClimSim awarded Best Paper Award at NeurIPS</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2312climsim/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2312climsim/</guid><description>ClimSim has been awarded Best Paper Award at NeurIPS ! The open large-scale dataset for training high-resolution physics emulators in hybrid multi-scale climate simulators, emerged out of the Science and Technology Center LEAP, received contributions from numerous M²LInES members. Congratulations to all authors!</description></item><item><title>Will Gregory's latest article featured in Advance Science News</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2312willgfeature/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2312willgfeature/</guid><description>The latest M²LInES article, led by Will Gregory (Princeton) is being featured in Advance Science News. The article details how Will and other colleagues, including M²LInES members Mitch Bushuk, Alistair Adcroft, and Laure Zanna, are using Machine Learning to enhance predictions of Arctic sea ice loss. Read the article by Giorgio Graffino here</description></item><item><title>OceanBench by J. Emmanuel Johnson</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2311johnson/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2311johnson/</guid><description>OceanBench is a suite of tools for designing experiments relevant to the oceanography community like interpolation, forecasting and estimation. Lead author J. Emmanuel Johnson and co-authors, including Anastasiia Gorbunova and Julien Le Sommer, demonstrate its use within a benchmark setting for sea surface height interpolation, using general circulation model simulations and real satellite observations.</description></item><item><title>UNetKF by Feiyu Lu</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2310lu/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2310lu/</guid><description>This study by Feiyu Lu incorporates deep learning methods to compliment and improve the ensemble Kalman filter data assimilation algorithm. More specifically, a convolutional neural network is trained to predict the error statistics of a model ensemble, which will reduce the computational costs of the ensemble Kalman filter. This approach is tested in a quasi-geostrophic dynamic model to demonstrate its feasibility in more advanced weather and climate applications.</description></item><item><title>Multi-fidelity climate model parameterization by Mohamed Aziz Bhouri</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2310bhouri/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2310bhouri/</guid><description>In this preprint , Mohamed Aziz Bhouri and co-authors, including Pierre Gentine, developed a probabilistic multi-fidelity atmospheric parameterization for heat and moisture tendency. They implemented it on CESM CAM5 and SPCAM5 data and showed its capabilities to well extrapolate to unseen warmer climate simulations while returning trustworthy uncertainty quantification.</description></item><item><title>Benefits of Deterministic and Stochastic Tendency Adjustments in a Climate Model</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2310chapman/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2310chapman/</guid><description>Stochastic and deterministic tendency adjustments are applied to multiple experiments in the community atmosphere model version 6. The tendency adjustments are gleaned from the DART data assimilation system and a linear relaxation towards ERA-interim reanalysis. In this preprint , Will Chapman and Judith Berner show that the tendency adjustment significantly enhances the representation of the background state climatology for key prognostic and surface variables. Additionally, they show that stochastic tendencies are essential to accurately represent model variability of major atmospheric modes when making tendency adjustments.</description></item><item><title> Blog Post - A New Generation of Climate Models</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2309blogpost/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2309blogpost/</guid><description>M²LInES can now demonstrate the impact of data-driven Machine Learning parameterizations in global models! 🌎You can read about new gen climate models with AI in our blog post</description></item><item><title>New climate simulation model ensemble by Marika Holland</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2309holland/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2309holland/</guid><description>Climate simulation uncertainties arise from internal variability, model structure, and external forcings. These uncertainty sources are difficult to disentangle across model generations because both model structure and external forcings typically change. This preprint , led by Marika Holland, presents new ensemble simulations which allow for the separation of uncertainty sources between two large ensembles (LEs) of the Community Earth System Model (CESM). Importantly, we find a strong influence of historical forcing uncertainty in differences between CESM1-LE and CESM2-LE due to aerosol effects on simulated climate.</description></item><item><title>Understanding Extreme Precipitation Changes by Griffin Mooers</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2309mooers/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2309mooers/</guid><description>Griffin Mooers is lead author in this preprint that leverages Variational Autoencoders on SPCAM5 output to examine the changes in the upper quantiles of precipitation between a control and warmed simulation. They find intense precipitation changes are mostly controlled by spatial shifts in deep convection.</description></item><item><title>Reliable coarse-grained turbulent simulations by Chris Pederson</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2309pederson/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2309pederson/</guid><description>In this preprint , M²LInES postdoc Chris Pedersen, along with Pavel Perezhogin, Joan Bruna, and Laure Zanna, show that the standard offline learning paradigm used to produce ML models of unresolved dynamics can be complemented with some learned time evolution of the system, and produce more stable hybrid physics and ML models.</description></item><item><title>Background Pycnocline depth constrains FOHUE by Emily Newsom</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2308newsom/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2308newsom/</guid><description>In this paper , Emily Newsom and co-authors Laure Zanna and Jonathan Gregory, showed that the relative depth of ocean heat sequestration, which varies widely across climate models and paces the rate of surface climate warming, is strongly correlated to interior ocean stratification. Using a novel regional decomposition method, they showed that this relationship is entirely driven by mid-latitude ventilation processes and explains 70% of the variance in heat penetration depth across CMIP5/CMIP6 models.</description></item><item><title>ClimSim: LEAP publication</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2308bhouri/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2308bhouri/</guid><description>Several of M²LInES members and affiliates (Bhouri, Gentine, Zanna, Abernathey, Busecke, Mooers, Shamekh, and Yuval) have contributed to this LEAP paper presenting ClimSim, the largest-ever dataset designed for hybrid ML-physics research. It comprises multi-scale climate simulations, global in coverage, spans multiple years at high sampling frequency, and is designed such that resulting emulators are compatible with downstream coupling into operational climate simulators. The data and code are open access.</description></item><item><title>Learning Atmospheric Boundary Layer Turbulence by Sara Shamekh</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2308shamekh/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2308shamekh/</guid><description>This preprint , by Sara Shamekh and Pierre Gentine, proposes a novel data-driven parameterization of vertical turbulent fluxes in convective boundary layer, that models the fluxes of various scalars across turbulent regimes. By incorporating a physics-based constraint this approach allows us to decompose the total vertical flux into two main modes of variability based on large scale forces that control the turbulence in the atmosphere.</description></item><item><title>Parameterizing vertical mixing coefficients in the Ocean by Akash Sane</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2307sane/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2307sane/</guid><description>Small scale vertical mixing processes in the upper ocean region cannot be resolved by ocean models due to the lack of computing resources, and are thus parameterized. Existing models have a few ad hoc approximations which cause uncertainty in climate change simulations. In this breakthrough preprint , Aakash Sane and co-authors - Brandon Reichl, Alistair Adcroft, and Laure Zanna - replace such an approximation using data driven neural networks (NN), leading to improved physics in an ocean model simulation and a reduction of model bias in the Tropics.</description></item><item><title>Smart correction model for winter sky temperatures by Lorenzo Zampieri</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2306zampieri/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2306zampieri/</guid><description>This study , led by Lorenzo Zampieri, and co-authored by Marika Holland, illustrates a novel method based on machine learning for reducing the systematic surface temperature errors that characterize multiple atmospheric reanalyses in sea-ice-covered regions of the Arctic under clear-sky conditions. The corrected reanalysis temperature can be employed to support polar research activities, and in particular to better simulate the evolution of the interacting sea ice and ocean system within numerical models.</description></item><item><title>Data-driven subgrid parameterizations by Karl Otness</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2305otness/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2305otness/</guid><description>In this ongoing project , Karl Otness and co-authors are evaluating a proof of concept multiscale approach to predicting subgrid forcings in climate models. They see encouraging preliminary results from first making a prediction in a fine-to-coarse direction which yields a lower resolution, but more confident prediction followed by a refinement to predict finer scale details.
This paper won “Best ML innovation” at the ICLR 2023 Workshop: Tackling Climate Change with Machine Learning.</description></item><item><title>Emulating Cloud Superparameterization by Pierre Gentine</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2301gentine/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2301gentine/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Pierre Gentine is the senior author in this new publication on using deep learning for emulating cloud superparameterization in climate models. Research Scientist Tom Beucler is a co-author. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title> M²LInES at AGU 22</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2212agu22/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2212agu22/</guid><description>AGU M²LInES Highlights The M²LInES team is excited to present our recent scientific advances at the Fall 2022 AGU meeting in Chicago and online. Below is a summary of the talks (all times are CST). For your convenience, you can download the schedule for the talks by following this link .
Machine learning for physics discovery &amp;amp; modeling We have an extensive lineup of talks and posters from M²LInES team members and affiliates.</description></item><item><title> Direct observational evidence of an oceanic dual kinetic energy cascade and its seasonality</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211balwada/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211balwada/</guid><description>In this article , led by Dhruv Balwada, ocean drifter observations show wave and turbulence merge and split flows, simultaneously transferring energy to large and small scales.</description></item><item><title> Implicit learning of convective organization explains precipitation stochasticity</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211shamekh/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211shamekh/</guid><description>Cloud and convection take many structure and degrees of organization, which are still absent in most parameterizations. But does that structure matter for precipitation? This preprint , led by Sara Shamekh, proposes an elegant method to include organization in the parameterization of precipitation that results in a significant improvement in predicting precipitation, especially extremes, at GCM scale.</description></item><item><title> Ocean currents break up a tabular iceberg</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211adcroft/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211adcroft/</guid><description>This article examines the mechanism that led to the breakup of massive iceberg A68 in Dec 2020. The authors, including Alistair Adcroft, demonstrate that the A68a breakup event may have been triggered by ocean-current shear, a new breakup mechanism not previously reported. Their paper was featured in the news .</description></item><item><title> On Gradient Descent Convergence beyond the Edge of Stability</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211bruna/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2211bruna/</guid><description>Joan Bruna is the senior author in this preprint on Gradient Descent (GD) convergence in unstable conditions. The study examines the conditions for such unstable convergence, focusing on simple, yet representative, learning problems.</description></item><item><title> A year-round satellite sea-ice thickness record from CryoSat-2</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2210bushuk/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2210bushuk/</guid><description>This study , co-authored by Mitch Bushuk, produced the first ever year-round satellite observational record of Arctic sea ice thickness, employing a deep learning model to produce estimates of sea ice freeboard. These data span the period 2010-2020 and will be critical for better monitoring the changing Arctic climate, advancing climate model evaluation, and improving sea ice predictions.</description></item><item><title> Comparing Storm Resolving Models and Climates via Unsupervised Machine Learning</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2210gentine/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2210gentine/</guid><description>High resolution data is overwhelming and this paper , co-authored by Pierre Gentine and Tom Beucler, tries to define an unsupervised machine learning technique to better compare Storm Resolving Climate Models (SRMs). Their analysis found that only six out of nine considered SRMs are dynamically consistent. This split among SRMs highlights the need to further investigate sub-grid parameterization choices.</description></item><item><title> Semi-automatic tuning of coupled climate models with multiple intrinsic timescales</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2210deshayes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2210deshayes/</guid><description>Using the two-scale Lorenz96 model, this article evaluates the potential of History Matching to tune a climate system with multi-scale dynamics. This semi-automatic tuning was more efficient when combined with physical expertise. Julie Deshayes and V Balaji are co-authors on this study.</description></item><item><title> Benchmarking of machine learning ocean subgrid parameterizations in an idealized model</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2208ross/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2208ross/</guid><description>In this work , led by Andrew Ross, with Ziwei Li, Pavel Perezhogin, Carlos Fernandez-Granda and Laure Zanna, we provide a framework for systematically benchmarking the offline and online performance of physical and ML-based subgrid parameterizations. We find that the choice of filtering operator is critical for performance. To help with interpretability, we also propose a novel equation-discovery approach combining linear regression and genetic programming which generalizes better than physical and neural network parameterizations.</description></item><item><title> Cloud-based framework for inter-comparing submesoscale permitting realistic ocean models</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2208uchida/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2208uchida/</guid><description>This study presents a cloud-based workflow for intercomparing high-resolution ocean models and provides an assessment of one of the most used parameterizations of ocean submesoscales. Julien Le Sommer, Ryan Abernathey, and Aurelie Albert contributed to the research.</description></item><item><title> Non-Linear Dimensionality Reduction with a VED to Understand Convective Processes in Climate Models</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2208behrens/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2208behrens/</guid><description>Pierre Gentine and Tom Beucler are co-authors in this article , which demonstrates that Variational Encoder Decoder structures (VED) are capable of learning and accurately reproducing convective processes in an aquaplanet superparameterized climate model simulation, while enabling interpretability and better understanding of sub-grid-scale physical processes.</description></item><item><title> A potential energy analysis of ocean surface mixed layers - Brandon Reichl</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2207reichl/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2207reichl/</guid><description>Analysis of the ocean mixed layer requires one to estimate its vertical extent, for which there are various definitions. In this paper , Brandon Reichl and co-authors, including Alistair Adcroft, show that using the potential energy anomaly to identify the mixed layer depth is practical and it offers conceptual benefits by directly linking to the physics of upper ocean vertical mixing.</description></item><item><title> New preprint led by Adam Subel on transfer learning</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2207subel/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2207subel/</guid><description>Adam Subel is the lead author in this article , which builds a framework to understand and implement transfer learning, a powerful machine learning technique for enabling generalization between datasets from different configurations of a system or of varying quality/quantity, in multiscale physical systems.</description></item><item><title> Subseasonal Earth System Prediction with CESM2 - Judith Berner</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2207berner/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2207berner/</guid><description>Judith Berner is a co-author in this article , which describes the design and prediction skill of two subseasonal prediction systems based on two configurations of the Community Earth System Model, version 2 (CESM2): with the Community Atmosphere Model and with Whole Atmosphere Community Climate Model as its atmospheric component. Both systems are compared to NOAA CFSv2 and ECMWF.</description></item><item><title> Deep Learning for Subgrid-Scale Turbulence Modeling in LES of the Convective Atmospheric Boundary Layer</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gentine-abernathey/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gentine-abernathey/</guid><description>This article , co-authored by Pierre Gentine and Ryan Abernathey, replaces the typically used physically based assumptions with deep learning in subgrid-scale modeling, in large eddy simulations of turbulence. They show that the latter performs better in a priori (offline) tests of atmospheric turbulence. The deep neural networks model also captures key statistics of turbulence in a posteriori (online) tests.</description></item><item><title> Lorenzo Zampieri - A machine learning correction model</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/zampieri2022/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/zampieri2022/</guid><description>Lorenzo Zampieri et al. illustrate in this preprint , a novel method based on ML for reducing the surface temperature errors of atmospheric reanalyses in sea-ice-covered regions of the Arctic. The corrected temperature can be employed to support polar research activities, and to better simulate the evolution of the interacting sea ice and ocean systems in numerical models.</description></item><item><title> Will Gregory - Network connectivity article</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gregory2022/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gregory2022/</guid><description>Will Gregory and co-authors hypothesized in this publication that regional biases in sea ice thickness may hinder the ability of CMIP6 models to reproduce an important atmospheric driver of summer sea ice variability, and hence their ability to make reliable sea ice predictions on seasonal to inter-annual time scales.</description></item><item><title> 2022 CESM workshop: Info and submission deadline</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/cesmworkshop2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/cesmworkshop2022/</guid><description>Registration is open for the 2022 CESM Workshop on June 13-16, 2022. Please visit the website to register as well as submit working group session talks and /or posters. The deadline to submit a talk / poster is Monday, May 16th.
The full workshop agenda can be found here .
In particular, Laure Zanna will give a joint plenary talk on M²LInES with Galen McKinley from LEAP.</description></item><item><title> Anastasiia Gorbunova - Eulerian spatiotemporal correlations in passive scalar turbulence</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gorbunova2021/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gorbunova2021/</guid><description>In this paper , Anastasiia Gorbunova and co-authors study spatio-temporal correlation function of a passive scalar in 3D homogeneous isotropic turbulence and synthetic velocity fields, by means of direct numerical simulations. Two regimes of temporal decorrelation are observed: a Gaussian at small time lags and exponential at large time lags. This behaviour is in agreement with recent analytical results.</description></item><item><title> GCM-Filters publication</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gcmfilter/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/gcmfilter/</guid><description>Ryan Abernathey, Arthur Guillaumin, Andrew Ross and Laure Zanna are co-authors of this article in JOSS presenting a new python package that allows scientists to perform spatial filtering analysis in an easy, flexible and efficient way. The package was initially developed as part of the Climate Process Team and will help further M²LInES goals of using data and ML to improve subgrid parameterizations.</description></item><item><title> Marika Holland - Arctic sea ice sensitivity to lateral melting representation</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/holland2022/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 08:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/holland2022/</guid><description>Marika Holland is a co-author in this research paper using a coupled climate model (CESM2.0) to assess the sensitivity of modeled sea ice state to the lateral melt parameterization, in preindustrial and 2×CO₂ runs.</description></item><item><title> Balaji - Are GCMs obsolete?</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/balaji2022/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 07:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/balaji2022/</guid><description>V Balaji and co-authors, including Julie Deshayes, describe in this paper the shortcomings of current GCMs and the methods in development to improve them. It is currently under review as a PNAS Perspective.</description></item><item><title> Adam Subel - Stable a posteriori LES of 2D turbulence using convolutional neural networks</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/220401subel/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/220401subel/</guid><description>Using 2D decaying turbulence as a testbed, this work , co-authored by Adam Subel, explores the importance of accurately capturing backscattering in generating stable online LES. Additionally, it shows that transfer learning can enable generalization to flows with a higher Reynolds number, even if an increase in resolution is needed.</description></item><item><title> Joan Bruna - Neural Galerkin Scheme preprint</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/220401bruna/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/220401bruna/</guid><description>Lead author Joan Bruna introduces in this preprint , a method to use deep neural network when training data are initially unavailable: Neural Galerkin schemes integrate time-dependent partial differential equations with deep networks by generating the data needed to advance their solution on-the-fly using importance sampling.</description></item><item><title> Mitch Bushuk on the Mechanisms of Regional Arctic Sea Ice Predictability</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/220401bushuk/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/220401bushuk/</guid><description>In this article , Mitch Bushuk and co-authors evaluate regional Arctic sea ice extent predictions made with the FLOR and SPEAR_MED dynamical seasonal forecast systems, and investigate the mechanisms of predictability in these systems. Feiyu Lu also contributed to the research.</description></item><item><title> Dhruv Balwada and Laure Zanna article in SIAM news</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/balwadazanna22/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/balwadazanna22/</guid><description>Dhruv Balwada and Laure Zanna published an article in SIAM news, detailing current insights on using Machine Learning for multiscale systems, particularly in the context of Climate prediction.</description></item><item><title>Movie about M²LInES and featured on AGU TV!</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/m2linesmovie/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/m2linesmovie/</guid><description>Check out the movie made about our project! It summarizes our goals and challenges and how we are planning to use Data and Machine Learning to address them.
A short version of the movie was featured on AGU TV (starting at 5:17):</description></item><item><title> Aakash Sane - Evaluating Coupled Climate Model Parameterizations</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/sanepaper2022/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/sanepaper2022/</guid><description>Aakash Sane is a co-author in this paper showing that ocean models having Langmuir turbulence and submesoscale restratification parameterizations give the most accurate simulation of monsoon intraseasonal oscillation events.</description></item><item><title> Book Chapter - Isopycnal mixing by Ryan Abernathey</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/abernatheychapter/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/abernatheychapter/</guid><description>In a new book chapter, Ryan Abernathey reviews both the frameworks to study isopycnal mixing and the recent insights gained from observations and simulations. This chapter lays the foundation on how isopycnal mixing is parametrized in ocean models.
Read the book chapter here</description></item><item><title>Climate-Invariant Machine Learning</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/beuclerpreprint/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/beuclerpreprint/</guid><description>Tom Beucler and co-authors demonstrate in this preprint , that physically rescaling the inputs and outputs of ML algorithms help them generalize to unseen climates and geographies. Janni Yuval, Paul O’Gorman and Pierre Gentine contributed to the research.</description></item><item><title>Deep Probability Estimation</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/fernandezgranda21/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/fernandezgranda21/</guid><description>Carlos Fernandez-Granda and co-authors, including Laure Zanna, investigate in this preprint , probability estimation from high-dimensional data using deep neural networks. In particular, they propose a new method for probability estimation, which outperforms existing approaches on simulated as well as on three real-world datasets (including climatology data).</description></item><item><title>Hugo Frezat - A posteriori learning of quasi-geostrophic turbulence parametrization</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/frezatpreprint/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/frezatpreprint/</guid><description>In this paper , Hugo Frezat, Julien Le Sommer, and their co-authors, train a NN-based closures for QG dynamics with an a posteriori learning criteria based on model integrations over several time-steps. While this strategy yields closures which outperform existing baselines, it requires the coarse resolution model to be differentiable in order to minimize the training loss.</description></item><item><title>Tropical precipitation clusters as islands on a rough water-vapor topography</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/ziweili21/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/ziweili21/</guid><description>Viewing precipitation clusters as islands on a rough column-water-vapor (CWV) topography, lead author Ziwei Li used self-affine theories to relate multiple scale-free statistics of precipitation clusters to the properties of CWV islands. Paul O’Gorman also contributed to the research. Read more .</description></item><item><title> AGU presentations by M²LInES team members</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/agupresentation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/agupresentation/</guid><description>Schedule of AGU presentations from team members Monday Dec 13th 12:53 CST Feiyu Lu “Prediction and Attribution of the Western North America heatwave in June-July of 2021”. Abstract
14:50 CST Will Chapman “Skillful Wintertime Temperature Forecasts out to 6 Weeks with Machine Learning Methods over the America&amp;rsquo;s”. Abstract
14:51 CST Janni Yuval “Neural-Network Parameterization of Subgrid Momentum Transport Learned from a High-Resolution Simulation”. Abstract
Tuesday Dec 14th 9:55 CST Ziwei Li “A Conceptual Model for Tropical Convective Organization”.</description></item><item><title> M²LInES Kickoff meeting</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/kickoffoct/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/kickoffoct/</guid><description>M²LInES Kickoff meeting on Oct 28th and 29th was tremendously successful! It gathered the team, including all our new and incoming hires, our funders, as well as the VESRI advisory board. It featured amazing talks and sparked insightful discussions. Thank you to all who joined us and thank you to our brilliant speakers: Laure Zanna, Pierre Gentine, Paul O’Gorman, Carlos Fernandez-Granda, Ryan Abernathey, Judith Berner and Alistair Adcroft.</description></item><item><title> The influence of snow on sea ice as assessed from simulations of CESM2 - Marika Holland</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/hollandetal/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/hollandetal/</guid><description>Lead author Marika Holland demonstrates in this paper the importance of accurately representing snow accumulation on sea-ice in coupled earth system models. Diagnosing snow and ice thickness heterogeneity will be a crucial part of the M²LInES project.</description></item><item><title> Probabilistic Predictions from Deterministic Atmospheric River Forecasts with Deep Learning - Will Chapman</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/chapmanetal/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/chapmanetal/</guid><description>In this paper , Will Chapman uses a deep learning (DL) based post-processing framework to generate probabilistic forecasts of atmospheric rivers from single member numerical weather prediction (NWP) forecasts. They show that the DL forecasts are reliable and sharp, and compete well with dynamically generated NWP ensembles.</description></item><item><title> Response of Northern Hemisphere Weather and Climate to Arctic Sea Ice Decline - Lorenzo Zampieri</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/zampierietal21/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/zampierietal21/</guid><description>Lorenzo Zampieri and his co-authors investigates in this study whether the simulated atmospheric midlatitude response to future changes in Arctic sea ice depends on the resolution of the atmospheric model.</description></item><item><title> UN AI for Good: AI and Climate Science seminars</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/aiforgood/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/aiforgood/</guid><description>UN AI for Good has announced their line up for their Fall/Winter Seminars. You can find the list of speakers for the AI and Climate Science seminars here .
In particular several M²LInES team members will be presenting on the following dates:
Paul O’Gorman - Nov 3rd Laure Zanna - Nov 10th. Pierre Gentine - Nov 17th</description></item><item><title>Adaptive Denoising via GainTuning - Carlos Fernandez-Granda</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/fernandezgranda/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/fernandezgranda/</guid><description>Carlos Fernandez-Granda and his team introduces a new technique for adaptive denoising of Deep convolutional neural networks. Available to read here as a preprint.</description></item><item><title>Impact of Sea-Ice Model Complexity on model performance by Lorenzo Zampieri</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/zampierijames/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/zampierijames/</guid><description>Incoming postdoc Lorenzo Zampieri demonstrates in this article how increased sea-ice model complexity can improve the simulated sea-ice concentration and snow thickness. Available to read in open access here .</description></item><item><title>Article by Dhruv Balwada et al. - Role of submesoscale flows on vertical fluxes</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/balwada-article/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/balwada-article/</guid><description>Dhruv Balwada is the lead author in this article analyzing the role of submesoscale flows on tracer fluxes. You can read it here (or in earthArXiv here ). Ryan Abernathey also contributed to the research.</description></item><item><title>Estimating Ocean Surface Currents With Machine Learning - Ryan Abernathey</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/abernatheypaper/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/abernatheypaper/</guid><description>Ryan Abernathey is the senior author in this publication where deep learning models are trained to effectively “learn” spatial gradients and the physics of surface currents. You can read it here .</description></item><item><title>Seasonal Prediction and Predictability of Regional Antarctic Sea Ice - Mitch Bushuk</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/bushukarticle/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/bushukarticle/</guid><description>In this article, lead author Mitch Bushuk uses the forecast system that his team will be using for M²LInES. You can read it here (or in Researchgate here ).</description></item><item><title>Neural Networks as Geometric Chaotic Maps - by Ziwei Li</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/ziweiliarticle/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/ziweiliarticle/</guid><description>M²LInES incoming postdoc Ziwei Li is the lead author on a new article on Neural Networks as Geometric Chaotic Maps. You can read it here (or in arXiv here ).</description></item><item><title>Neural network parametrization of a subgrid process - by Janni Yuval and Paul O'Gorman</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/articleyuval/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/articleyuval/</guid><description>A new M²LInES scientific paper on Neural-network parameterization of subgrid momentum transport in the atmosphere, by members Janni Yuval and Paul O&amp;rsquo;Gorman, is available to read as a preprint here .</description></item><item><title> Article in Eos by Yuval et al. - Call for Papers on Machine Learning and Earth System Modeling</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/articlejamescall/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/articlejamescall/</guid><description>M²LInES members Janni Yuval is the lead author in this article inviting scientists to contribute to a new special collection in Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems (JAMES). The collection will focus on the use of new machine learning methodologies and applications of machine learning to Earth system modeling. Pierre Gentine and Laure Zanna are co-authors of the article.
Link to contribute to the special collection in JAMES here</description></item><item><title> Upcoming Seminar by Laure Zanna at One World Mathematics of Climate - 7/6</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/oneworld/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/oneworld/</guid><description>M²LInES lead PI Laure Zanna will give a seminar at the One World Mathematics of Climate on July 6th 12pm EST. She will talk about some of the machine learning work on ocean eddy parameterization and about the work being done at M²LInES. Tune in here</description></item><item><title> A Bayesian approach towards sea ice freeboard estimates - paper by Will Gregory</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/willgregorypaper/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/willgregorypaper/</guid><description>Incoming M²LInES postdoc Will Gregory is the lead author in this new publication on using a Bayesian approach towards sea ice freeboard estimates from satellite observations.
This work has 3 important implications: 1) a daily freeboard product allows them, for the first time, to assess radar freeboard (and ultimately sea ice thickness) variability on sub-weekly timescales &amp;ndash; it takes up to 1 month for each satellite to generate pan-Arctic coverage alone.</description></item><item><title> s2s challenge</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/s2schallenge/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 10:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/s2schallenge/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Judith Berner is setting up a team to participate to the s2s challenge, which goal is to improve sub-seasonal to seasonal predictions using AI. M²LInES postdocs Janni Yuval and Tarun Verma will also be part of the team. The deadline to register is July 1st 2021. More info here</description></item><item><title> KITP conference: Machine Learning for Climate</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/kitpconference/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 10:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/kitpconference/</guid><description>M²LInES Lead PI Laure Zanna is the co-director of the next conference on Machine Learning for Climate of the Kavli Institute for Theoretical Physics (KITP) . It will take place Nov 1-4 2021. Info and registration here</description></item><item><title> 2021 CESM workshop: M²LInES team members presenting on June 17th</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/cesmworkshop/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/cesmworkshop/</guid><description>M²LInES team members will present at Machine Learning session for the CESM workshop on June 17. Info and agenda here</description></item><item><title> Call for Papers for JAMES</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/5jamescall/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/5jamescall/</guid><description>M²LInES members Janni Yuval, Pierre Gentine and Laure Zanna are part of the organizers of a special collection at JAMES (Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems) that will include both new ML methodologies developed for advancing Earth system science and ML applications to Earth system modeling. Papers submissions are open. The community is invited to contribute. More information here</description></item><item><title>Using deep learning to emulate cloud superparameterization - new paper by PI Gentine</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/3gentinepaper1/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/3gentinepaper1/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Pierre Gentine is the senior author in this new publication on using deep learning for emulating cloud superparameterization in climate models. Research Scientist Tom Beucler is a co-author. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title> Neural Network emulating physical constraints - paper by PI Gentine</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/4gentinepaper2/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/4gentinepaper2/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Pierre Gentine is the senior author and Research Scientist Tom Beucler is the lead author in this new publication on enforcing analytic constraints in Neural Networks emulating physical systems. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title> New paper on deep learning parametrization by Guillaumin and Zanna</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/1guillauminpaper/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/1guillauminpaper/</guid><description>In this paper, M²LInES postdoc Arthur Guillaumin and lead PI Laure Zanna developed a stochastic deep learning parametrization that is trained on high-resolution data from CM2.6, a coupled climate model. Read their paper here</description></item><item><title> Modelisation using neural network - paper by PI Le Sommer</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2jlesommerpaper/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 09:29:16 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/news/2jlesommerpaper/</guid><description>M²LInES PI Julien Le Sommer is a co-author in this new publication using neural network to model subgrid-scale processes. Read their paper here</description></item></channel></rss>