<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blog on M²LInES</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Blog on M²LInES</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://m2lines.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Data Assimilation</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/blog/dataassimilation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/blog/dataassimilation/</guid><description>Climate models &amp; observations Climate models are powerful tools to simulate and predict the Earth’s climate system, but they aren&amp;rsquo;t without flaws. Due to missing physics, imperfect parameterizations, and inaccuracies in the underlying numerics, climate models often show structural errors. On the other hand we have direct observations of the climate system. However, observations come with their own set of limitations. They have limited space and time coverage and also contain errors due to measurement noise.</description></item><item><title>Machine Learning</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/blog/machinelearning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/blog/machinelearning/</guid><description>Machine learning methodologies, particularly neural networks, are computer algorithms inspired by the structure and function of the human brain. These algorithms are capable of learning from data, identifying patterns, and making predictions or decisions without being explicitly programmed. Neural networks consist of interconnected nodes organized into layers, including input, hidden, and output layers. During training, they adjust the strength of connections between nodes, called weights, based on examples from a dataset, allowing them to learn complex patterns and relationships in the data.</description></item><item><title>Ocean</title><link>https://m2lines.github.io/blog/ocean/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://m2lines.github.io/blog/ocean/</guid><description>Ocean modeling and turbulence Figure: The ocean circulation is composed of many coherent features distributed over a wide range of scales. Snapshot of surface relative vorticity (swirliness) from a global 1/10 degree simulation with MOM6, showing the presence of ocean eddies, sharp boundary currents, tropical instability waves, shelf circulations, etc.
The ocean is a turbulent fluid, in which motions on a wide range of scales – from centimeters to thousands of kilometers – interact and exchange energy.</description></item></channel></rss>