<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>M²LInES</title>
    <link>/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content on M²LInES</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Deepening our understanding of key climate processes</title>
      <link>/research/research1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/research1/</guid>
      <description>We will enhance our understanding of key climate processes using two types of data: 1. Data from high-resolution simulation and observations. 2. Data resulting from model errors, also called data assimilation increments.
M²LInES will be focusing on processes happening in the ocean, atmosphere and sea-ice. Below is a representation of the physical processes that will be studied by the team:
From high-resolution simulations and observational data We will diagnose small-scale physical processes such as:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing new physics-aware machine learning tools</title>
      <link>/research/research2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/research2/</guid>
      <description>Learning from the high resolution data, as well as from model errors (Data Assimilation Increments), we will develop Machine Learning algorithms that are physics- and scale-aware to accelerate climate science discovery .
Our transformative methodology will rely on a range of ML algorithms (e.g., convolutional neural networks, equation-discovery), including with strict physical constraints, or with embeded physics for improved interpretability, and generalizations.
Those ML models will be used to deepen our understanding of subgrid processes, and will be implemented as subgrid parameterizations or as bias corrections, in coarser resolution ocean (NEMO and MOM6) and coupled climate models (IPSLCM, CM4, CESM).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving coupled climate models</title>
      <link>/research/research3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/research3/</guid>
      <description>Predicting future climate conditions on earth, and in particular, the impacts of climate change, would not be possible without climate models. Climate models are complex mathematical representations of the physical processes happening in each of the climate system components: ocean, atmosphere, sea-ice and land surface, as well as their interactions with each other.
Climate models divide the globe into three dimensional grid cells representing a specific location and elevation. The resolution of the models, their “level of detail”, is dependent on the size chosen for the grid cells: the smaller the grid size the higher the resolution.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
