<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>M²LInES</title>
    <link>/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content on M²LInES</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Deepening our understanding of key climate processes</title>
      <link>/research/research1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/research1/</guid>
      <description>We will be deepening our understanding of key climate processes using two types of data: 1. Data from high-resolution simulation and observations. 2. Data resulting from model errors, also called data assimilation increments.
From high-resolution simulations and observational data We will diagnose small-scale physical processes such as:
 Atmospheric convection and clouds (O&amp;rsquo;Gorman) Atmospheric boundary layer processes at the ocean and sea-ice interface (Gentine) Ocean mesoscale buoyancy fluxes (Abernathey) Ocean submesoscale processes (LeSommer) Ocean mesoscale momentum, energy and air-sea interactions (Zanna) Vertical mixing (Adcroft/Reichl) Sea-ice heterogeneity and its influence on air-sea-ice interactions (Holland)  We will also learn from the data resulting from model errors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing new physics-aware machine learning tools</title>
      <link>/research/research2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/research2/</guid>
      <description>Learning from the high resolution data, as well as from model errors (Data Assimilation Increments), we will develop Machine Learning algorithms that are physics- and scale-aware to accelerate climate science discovery .
Our transformative methodology will rely on a range of ML algorithms (e.g., convolutional neural networks, equation-discovery), including with strict physical constraints, or with embeded physics for improved interpretability, and generalizations.
Those ML models will be used to deepen our understanding of subgrid processes, and will be implemented as subgrid parameterizations or as bias corrections, in coarser resolution ocean (NEMO and MOM6) and coupled climate models (IPSLCM, CM4, CESM).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving coupled climate models</title>
      <link>/research/research3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/research3/</guid>
      <description>Our machine learning parameterizations will be implemented in coupled climate models from leading modeling centers(NCAR, GFDL, IPSL) to enhance climate projections
The aim of the Machine Learning parameterizations for coarse-resolution models will be to achieve comparable accuracy to high-resolution global simulations or observations.
Learn more: Learn more about the challenges in modelling the oceans for climate in this presentation by Alistair Adcroft, M²LInES head of modeling</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
